A Guide to the Papers of Julian Wehr, 1885-2004, n.d. (bulk 1943-1949)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Julian Wehr 1885-2004, n.d. (bulk 1943-1949)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12250
ca. 355 items (2 Hollinger boxes, .5 linear feet)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Julian Wehr papers were given to the University of Virginia Library by his children, David A. Wehr, Sugar Land, Texas; Paul E. Wehr, Boulder, Colorado; and Jeanine Wehr Jones, Raleigh, North Carolina on May 31, 2002.
Biographical/Historical Information
Julian Wehr began working with a lithographing company during his senior year of school, studying drawing and sculpture and drawing at night. He joined the United States Merchant Marine in 1917-1918, but returned to the world of art on his return home with wood carving and sculpture. At the Art Students League of New York, Wehr studied with John Sloan and Max Weber. He and fellow student Marguerite West married and had a daughter, Camilla.
After a trip to Italy in 1926 where he spent a year in study, he began work with ceramics and the design of metal ornamental doors. Julian and Marguerite lived in California, eventually divorcing in 1932. Julian moved to New York City and began a fruitful career in lithography.
He and Juliette Laubinger (1906-1993) married in 1933. Julie Laubinger was a graduate of Evander Childs High School and earned her degree from Hunter College in 1929. She became an art teacher at Abraham Lincoln High School in Brooklyn after her graduation.
In 1938, Wehr's animations for children's books were patented as "moving illustrations" that move the picture up and down and horizontally at the same time with a single movement. His designs were operated by tabs which are located at the bottom and sides of the pages of the book and moved back and forth through slits in the pages. As described by his son, Paul Wehr, his patented idea was "a background picture with parts moved by a tab-manipulated template interlocking those parts. The template was suspended from a fixed point, a rocker design, permitting the components to move back and forth, up and down, around, in and out--according to the reader's will." (The quote is from an article by Paul Wehr, "Love's Animation," on a website about the work of Julian Wehr [http://www.wehranimations.com]).
The first book designed by Julian Wehr to enter the moveable book market in 1942 was The Exciting Adventures of Finnie the Fiddler. The artwork for this title is well represented in this collection. Most of Julian's work with moveable books was with Duenewald Printing in the years 1943-1946.
Scope and Content
The papers of artist and book animator, Julian Wehr (1898-1970), consist of ca. 355 items (2 Hollinger boxes, .5 linear feet), 1885-2004, and undated, and contain animated panels, correspondence, illustrations, mock-ups for Mother Goose, three compact disks with digital images of his work along with a list of the images digitized by Digital Services, patents and licensing agreements, tracings, and artist tools belonging to Julian Wehr.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Contents List
- Animated Panels for Alice in Wonderland n.d. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Animated Panels for Finnie the Fiddler (also includes oversize) n.d. (Box-folder 1:2)
- Animated Panels for Jack and the Beanstalk n.d. (Box-folder 1:3)
- Animated Panels for Miscellaneous n.d. (Box-folder 1:4)
- Animated Panels for Mother Goose n.d. (Box-folder 1:5)
- Animated Panels for Peter Rabbit n.d. (Box-folder 1:6)
- Animated Panels for Raggedy Ann and Andy n.d. (Box-folder 1:7)
- Animated Panels for The Three Bears n.d. (Box-folder 1:8)
- Animated Panels for Toy Town and Toyland n.d. (Box-folder 1:9)
- Article--"Love's Animation" by Paul Wehr 2004 Oct (Box-folder 1:10)
- Book-- Finnie the Fiddler by Julian Wehr 1942, Electrostatic copy (Box-folder 1:11)
- Compact Discs containing digital images of Julian Wehr artwork in this collection ca. 2002 May (Othertype Compact Discs 0310, 0310-a, 0310-b)
- Compact Disc Julian Wehr: an artist's life through the eyes of his children.2006 (Othertype Compact Disc 0394)
- Correspondence concerning Patents 1941-1951 (Box-folder 1:12)
  chiefly with Edward Gottlieb, patent attorney, but also including Maxwell M. Booxbaum, attorney representing Wehr in Ridgefield v. Julian Wehr; Duenewald Publishing Company; and Jenter Associates
- Correspondence of Julian Wehr and Julie Wehr and Wehr and his editor 1945, n.d. (Box-folder 1:13)
- Illustrations n.d. (Box-folder 1:14)
- Lists of Julian Wehr Tracings and Prototypes copied on compact discs and copies of book covers and other illustrations from a search for Wehr on the internet 2001-2002 (Box-folder 1:15)
- Mock-up for Mother Goose with Animated Pictures by Julian Wehr with original artwork cover n.d., 26 x 19.5 cm (Box-folder 1:16)
- Mock-up for Mother Goose with Animated Pictures by Julian Wehr with original artwork cover and some prototypes n.d., 26 x 17.5 cm (Box-folder 1:17)
- Mock-up for Animated Mother Goose with Animated Pictures by Julian Wehr with original artwork cover n.d., 26 x 17.5 cm (Box-folder 1:18)
- Patents (printed) 1885-1945 (Box-folder 1:19)
- Patents belonging to Julian Wehr 1940-1950 (Box-folder 1:20)
- Patents and Licensing Agreements 1941-1949 (Box-folder 1:21)
- Photograph of Queen Mary viewing animated Snow White and an article concerning Julian Wehr n.d. (Box-folder 1:22)
- Tracings for Animated Antics in Playland, Animated Animals, and The Animated Circus 1943, 1946 (Box-folder 1:23)
- Tracings for Animated Nursery Tales, Animated Picture Book 4 Lively Stories About "Chubby" Billy and "Spotty", and Alice in Wonderland ca. 1943-1949 (Box-folder 1:24)
- Tracings for Brave Tin Soldier, The Gingerbread Boy, and Jack and the Beanstalk ca. 1943-1949 (Box-folder 1:25)
- Tracings for Finnie the Fiddler (also includes oversize) [1942] (Box-folder 1:26)
- Tracings for Little Black Sambo, Raggedy Ann and Andy, and The Tale of Peter Rabbit Ca. 1943-1949 (Box-folder 2:1)
- Tracings for The Little Engine That Could, Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs, and The Three Bears Ca. 1945-1949, n.d. (Box-folder 2:2)
- Tracings--Miscellaneous n.d. (Box-folder 2:3)
- Tracings for Mother Goose (also includes oversize) ca. 1942-1945 (Box-folder 2:4)
- Artist Tools of Julian Wehr (also includes oversize) n.d. (Box-folder 2:5)